[Music]
so
hello everybody welcome to episode 49 of
the ask abidjit show
i hope you are all doing well it's great
to be back with you this saturday
evening here in india
so let's see who all we have with us i
can see rajat kingster gaming harsh jain
sharma
indocannak harshit
gujjar animations eagle i yashlotra aj
rana rohan gupta
[Music]
it's great to see you all thank you so
much for being here
so what shall we talk about my friends
we shall talk about whatever you wish to
talk about what questions do you have
what do you want to discuss
let's see what you all are commenting
let's see
all right let's take a look at a few
comments
let us see let us see let us see i can
see lots of highs and hellos
okay okay let's start uh somewhere here
let okay this is by varade dongre varad
says varad asks
did india have any trade relations with
carthage
also was there any military exchange
considering the extensive use of war
elephants in war strategy
so for those of you who don't know
carthage is a
was
a
very prominent city city-state
civilization you could say in northern
africa
and they were
very strong rivals and
adversaries of the roman empire
and uh
hannibal barker one of the one of the
generals of carthage actually invaded
italy invaded the roman empire
inflicted a number of massive defeats
on the roman military machine
but he was eventually defeated and
eventually carthage was invaded
successfully by the roman empires and
raised to the ground
so that is what carthage was it's i
think in morocco in north africa
present-day morocco i think somewhere
there
so did india have any trade relations
with carthage i do not know because
carthage was entirely destroyed
annihilated by the roman empire
and
if there was any such trade relations or
any such thing all the traces all the
evidence has been destroyed by the
romans about 2
100 or so years ago
so we don't know
whether we had trade relations or
military exchange or anything like that
with the carthaginians
we do know there was extensive trade
between india and the roman empire
we have found lots of roman coins roman
uh jugs amphorae
in india
and there is a there is plenty of
evidence of indian uh artifacts in
italy in in rome
they have even they even archaeologists
even found a
figurine figurine a statuette
uh that seems to depict the goddess
lakshmi or or some indian goddess in the
ruined city of pompeii pompei if you
know
it was an ancient roman city that was uh
destroyed by mount vesuvius the eruption
of the volcano mount vesuvius about 2000
years before today approximately
so there was extensive
trade
cultural exchange etc between india and
rome it is possible
since carthage was not that far it was
just across the mediterranean south of
rome south of italy so it's certainly
possible that there may have been a
trade and other contacts between india
and carthage we know that india has
a very ancient history of contacts with
africa
um we find as indian zebu cattle in
africa we find evidence of zebu cattle
in egypt i think about 2000 bce or
thereabouts you know so
so it's it's very possible that there
may have been trade relations between
india and carthage unfortunately we
don't seem to have found any traces of
that because carthage was destroyed
flattened by the romans
they had vowed to destroy carthage
entirely and they were able to succeed
in that
so i hope that answers your question of
course it's not a definitive answer but
that's the evidence that we have as of
today
right let's see some more questions
uniform tango asks why was warfare
technology so poor in india during the
late ancient and early
medieval eras of history
i'm not sure what exactly you mean by
late ancient ancient is very ancient i
mean india's history
the archaeological record goes back 10
000 years so i'm not sure what exactly
even by ancient but when we talk about
the medieval era of history early
medieval i think you're talking about
the
period of history that's about 1 000
years before today around 1080
1000 ce
so that is when you had these turkic
invasions wave upon wave of turkic
invasions into india
and eventually india india did fall to
the turkic invasions these multiple
waves of turkic invasions
the thing is that it wasn't india's
warfare technology that was poor
india had
excellent
warriors excellent armies we had
excellent technology as well
some people have claimed that
uh
we did not have sufficient horses
perhaps but even that doesn't seem to be
true
that the reason why india fell to these
invasions is because india was not
united
and because that's the reason number one
reason number two is that
our
kings leaders etc were unnecessarily
generous and magnanimous towards the
enemy
they forgot that it was there it is
their duty it is the king's duty or the
queen's duty
to serve their people
and their kingdom
so the
long-term prosperity of the people in
the kingdom
has to be placed above everything else
above showing mercy towards your enemy
so for instance that that uh guy what's
his name gory right mahmud
was it gory was it ghaznavi one of those
two guys
uh he invaded india multiple times
one of the first invasions
during one of his first invasions
uh maharani nayaki devi
uh rajput queen
of gujarat i think
of gujarat yes
she met this guy in open battle
she led the army in
in battle in in the in the battle
so she was there at the front of the
army and there was this battle and he
was defeated
right
he was defeated his army was destroyed
and she allowed him to go back to
afghanistan to ghazni ghaznavi right
muhammad
ghaznavi that there's no terrorist
so maharani niki devi showed magnanimity
she forgave him and she allowed him to
go back to afghanistan when his army was
destroyed when he had lost the battle it
was certainly possible for her to order
her troops her cavalry etc try to go
pursue the guy and kill him finish it
off she'll finish him off she did not do
that
he escaped later on he came back to
india in another invasion this time shri
prithvira
defeated him and forgave him and let him
go and see these are the reasons why
india
eventually fell to these
turkic invasions it's not because of
poor technology or any such thing we had
the we had excellent technology we had
excellent warriors we had better
resources than any ragtag barbarian from
central asia
it's the the problem was that we had our
leaders had forgotten
what their
real duty was
and because they were not united they
were all at cross purposes so these are
the reasons why india lost it's not
because of poor
uh technology yeah people do get the
impression that we were
our technology and everything was poor
at the time but that's not the case
right let's take some more questions
shivaji rajee asks
how many questions do we have here uh
sir when are you making a video about
nehru and congress 99 blunders history
of arunachal and why china claims it can
we use christian missionaries to solve
the kashmir issue
and was jai chand a traitor
okay um
okay let me answer a couple of these
questions when am i making a video about
nehru and all his blunders
uh that's that's a good suggestion maybe
i will do it soon
history of arunachal that's a long story
uh why china claims it they claim it
because they want more and more
territory they want to keep india on the
back foot this is one of the uh tactics
one of the strategies that you use in
geopolitics
it is something that china is really
adept at they have used the same against
russia in the past in the 1960s etc
and they paid a heavy price for that
actually and now they're doing it
against india they're doing the same
thing in the south china sea salami
slicing creeping uh normalcy that sort
of thing you know
so this is a
tried and tested strategy of china and
one of the other reasons why that they
claim arunachal pradesh is because
arunachal pradesh has this town of
tawang which is one of the
major cultural centers
of the tibetan culture the sixth dalai
lama was born in tawang
and therefore they want the city of
tawang to claim legitimacy over tibetan
buddhism see the his holiness the dalai
lama is
quite elderly now he i think he's in his
eighties now if i'm not mistaken
so maybe he has another 20 years to live
maybe 30 if if
if he lives an exceptionally long life
but
you know he is now at the stage where he
needs to decide about his succession
who's going to be the next dalai lama
and the
the way the next dalai lama is chosen is
that once
the current dalai lama
passes away
he is
believed to be reborn
in a in the uh shape of a
newborn tibetan child
and then the tibetan uh clergy the
llamas etc they searched the entire
country for a child that has certain
signs
and those signs are all predefined etc
so when they discover a child that has
those signs
those characteristics then they
uh
confer the title of the new dalai lama
to the child so it's a succession across
births that's
that is a tradition in tibet
so it is
all in the hands of his holiness the
dilemma right now
to declare
where he will reincarnate
will he reincarnate in tibet in chinese
occupied tibet or will he reincarnate in
the diaspora outside of tibet maybe in
tawa maybe
maybe somewhere else
so this is the succession
that the chinese are worried about
because they want to appoint their own
dalai lama
and if the current dalai lama says that
that is illegitimate then the chinese
attempt to hijack the institution of the
dalai lama will fail or it will not have
sufficient legitimacy
the chinese want to uh take over
this institution of the dalai lama they
want to take over the birthplace of the
sixth dalai lama who is one of the most
prominent
dalai lamas and so on
so these are the reasons these are some
of the reasons why china is claiming
arunachal pradesh
they want to keep india on the back foot
geopolitically military etc they want to
reclaim not reclaim they want to usurp
the last uh best in the last stronghold
of tibetan buddhism
from the tibetans
because
india has
given shelter to the tibetans they have
they have been able to make india their
home hopefully temporarily hopefully
they'll go back to tibet when it's
free again
so these are some of the reasons why
china is playing these games
the other questions
can we use christian missionaries to
solve the kashmir issue that's a very
creative suggestion i'm not sure how one
would do that but yeah it's something
well that's a that's an out of the box
suggestion very interesting i must
upload the
creative
thinking maybe it's something that could
be used you can there are there's a
multitude of
strategies and tactics one can use
to solve a given problem so maybe this
is an interesting uh
interesting way of looking at it
and the last question is was jai chand a
traitor maharaja jai chandra was not a
traitor he has been portrayed as a
traitor in that stupid poem written by
chandra bardai
in which he said that jai chand chandra
was an anti-national traitor etc he also
claims that pithirak chohan killed that
that
what was it ghaznavi was he or gory one
of those two i think it was ghaznavi he
was taken to ghazni but he was but he
was able to kill
mahmoud ghaznavi and all that's all
nonsense so the truth is that maharaja
chandra was not a traitor but he has
been unfairly portrayed like that
because of that poem this chant bardai
wrote
all right let's take some more questions
guys girls questions questions come on
oh i can see there are lots of questions
i think i missed a few of those let me
find
some all right let's see some
questions
vishal mahajan says what do you think
about the india-bangladesh enclaves swap
in 2015 was it a right move
keeping in mind india's relations with
bangladesh so that's a very good
question if you look at the india
bangladesh border there are all these
enclaves and enclaves within enclaves
and all that we had in the past i think
they're still
a lot of
complicated
uh
boundary boundaries right now even now
between indian bangladesh but you had
all these ridiculous enclaves between so
what's an enclave
an enclave is
a territory
that belongs to one nation but it is
within the territory of another nation
so it's like an island of sorts and you
had these hundreds of enclaves indian
enclaves in bangladesh territory and
bangladeshi enclaves in indian territory
and it's all something that was left
over from history
but that made things incredibly
complicated and
so in 2015 there was a major swap of
enclaves that has significantly
reduced the complexity of the of the
india bangladesh border i think it was a
good thing
we need to keep things as simple as
possible especially when you have a
nation that is
oh well historically has been part of
your country country of your territory
etc it's always good to keep things
simple so that there are no unnecessary
complications
and
there's no unnecessary controversy so it
is a good move i think most of it has
been solved now i think it was a very
good move
and we need to work on the relationship
with bangladesh especially the border
which needs to be closed i hope one of
these days
so yeah so i think it was a good move
um let's see some more questions
karthik asks was gandhi's effort to
bring
freedom in africa genuine why he fought
in africa
uh mohandas gandhi did not ever try to
uh
to obtain freedom for the people of
africa he did not ever do that
if you look at his own writings he
considered uh
the
native people of africa to be
lower than
the
white the whites and the indians he
clearly wrote this that he believed that
the white race or the european race
should be the predominating race
the indians should come second and he
considered the african people to be the
lowest of the races so
you know this is this is racism
there's no other way to put it this is
something that he himself wrote it is in
his in his own writings it is available
online if you know where to look
uh there is this website called the
collected works of mohandas gandhi or
mahatma gandhi whatever
so you can look it up there all his
writings are available online for free
it's tedious to to read through it but
it's all there
now some people say that you know what
gandhi changed afterwards he may have
held certain beliefs when he was younger
but afterwards he became a proponent of
humanitarianism and freedom for all in
peace and
and and and what's it called
non-violence
and compassion and equality and all the
nonsense my point is very simple
i agree that people do change
what the things i may have believed 20
years ago are not what i believe today i
have evolved over the past two decades
everybody evolves
if you don't evolve we mean something's
wrong with you so yes people do evolve
but when somebody like mohandas gandhi a
very prominent person put something in
writing
that he may later
think was wrong
then he would write about it again and
say and put it on the record that yes i
believed these things 20 years ago 25
years ago but today i have realized i
was wrong it was wrong to think that way
but he never did that
he never expressed any form of regret
for the things that he wrote and the
things that he put out in the public
domain about the african people
if he had a change of heart later on
if he felt that what i said was wrong it
was racist it was
it was not the right thing to say then
he would have apologized or he would
have at least said that i was wrong i
was young i was immature and today i
understand that such beliefs that
certain people based on the color of the
screen our skin are inferior to us that
belief is completely wrong he never did
that
and therefore he is a racist
so it's clear as day that he never
changed his mind
he never wrote anything
uh
that went against what he had written
about the africans so the thing is he
never tried to bring freedom to the
people of africa
and
he served the british for 20-25 years in
south africa
and because of his service for such a
long period of time the british brought
him to india put him at the head of the
congress party and gave him the task of
shepherding and delaying
india's
quest for independence so that's about
mr gandhi
papaya sardar says
did hind
will hinduism vanish in the next 100
years it is a
a definite possibility
it is a definite possibility that
hinduism will vanish or become uh
marginalized or become minority uh
culture in india in the next 100 years
because see hinduism is
not like the abrahamic religions
hinduism is not expansionist hinduism
doesn't believe in converting people
aggressively or even non-aggressively
so
and and hinduism doesn't believe in
violence and fighting back and all that
and because of the gandhian ideology etc
the people of india the hindus
especially have become extremely passive
react non-reactive and so on
and these other religions are definitely
expanding very aggressively they have
enormous amounts of funding coming from
coming in from various parts of the
world
so their footprint is increasing
hinduism is decreasing
hinduism is something that needs state
support it's always been that way for
the past god knows how many thousands of
years without state support something
like hinduism will
shrivel away vanish and die
and today as you know there is
absolutely no state support for hinduism
the government doesn't support hinduism
in any shape or form
even the hindu temples are being
looted by the government i mean there's
no other way to put it
there's no over the put it in the hindu
temples
are all in the are all
hijacked by the government they are
administered by the government hindus
don't have the right to run their own
temples to administer their own temples
and whatever funds the temple generates
through donations by people by devotees
are all stolen by the government for
various
purposes whatever those purposes are
so i have said this in the past i will
say it again today that india is
the world's most hindu phobic country
even in the u.s hindus have more
equality
in india hindus are second class or
third large citizens so india is a hindu
phobic apartheid state and because of
that it is quite possible that hinduism
may very much may very well vanish
or become
irrelevant
in the next 100 years unless the people
themselves wake up and take certain
measures certain steps
okay more questions
some more questions
okay sir
um
according to thermodynamics this is by
pradeep pandey according to
thermodynamics energy cannot be created
or not destroyed so how did it come into
existence
that's the first question so that's an
interesting question the energy came
into existence because of what the mass
energy that was present at the time of
the
big bang
so as we know according to the best data
the best theory that we have the
standard model of physics according to
this model the entire universe
came into existence
from an initial singularity or near
singularity
which is the big bang that that process
is colloquially colloquially called the
big bang it was not an explosion it was
an expansion of space and time so all
that energy and mass was already present
therein and that's where it came from so
all the mass all the energy that's
present in the universe today it was all
concentrated in an in fight as
infinitesimally small
point
so all of space time had shrunk into
either a singularity or something very
close to that
so that's where all the energy or mass
which are interchangeable that's where
it all comes from that's where it came
into existence
from now what was there before the big
bang we have absolutely no idea so
so that's the answer to your question
the second question is opinions on
rashmi theory
it is said it challenges modern physics
is it bogus i have never studied it
unfortunately i haven't had the time
i i don't know what it is
maybe i i know this this is a question i
get all the time
many people have asked this question
unfortunately i have not had the time to
uh
search for it or look for it or i don't
know i i don't know as of today what it
is
so unfortunately i still cannot answer
the question i will try and look it up
one of these days hopefully soon and
then i will give an answer about
rashbi theory whatever that is sir
okay
karl bhairav says
is it possible for
man to achieve immortality in the
distant future or can we or can store
their consciousness
in some machine
i don't think it's possible for humans
to achieve immortality any time in the
near future
immortality means the uh
the immortality of the body obviously
now we know that there is a process of
aging and after a certain point the body
becomes non-functional it just can't
sustain life
and so that that is what leads to
eventual death after a certain age in
all humans
so how do you
either reverse or even pause the process
of aging that's what many
biologists and researchers are trying to
figure out but
it seems to be connected to the uh
shortening of what's called the
telomeres
inside cells
so
the telomeres are what
are the ends of the chromosomes and
these telomeres they shorten with time
as a person ages and maybe this it is
believed that this is what contributes
to the aging process of humans so it is
believed that if we can
either stop or reverse the shortening of
telomeres in human cells
then maybe we may be able to either
pause or reverse aging so that's a
possibility it is still a theory it is
maybe there is some proof of it perhaps
to some extent so that is what they're
working on but that's still a very
distant
dream i believe it's still a distant
dream
storing your consciousness it's still
science fiction we don't even know what
consciousness is
what shape or what is it an emergent
property is it something else we have
absolutely no idea what of what
consciousness is we don't even have a
clear definition
of
what consciousness is what is
consciousness we can't even define it
clearly
and therefore
um
therefore it's it's uh very hard to see
this happening anytime in the future
near future even far future
of being able to store upload your
consciousness into some machine and
let's say hypothetically theoretically
that you're able to take a copy of your
consciousness and and store it in a
machine
but that doesn't mean
that you're going to live forever that
your consciousness is going to be alive
forever it's a copy of your
consciousness
that's going to live in that machine but
your consciousness is eventually going
to die with your body
it's like the um the scenario in star
trek if any of you have seen star trek
there is this
teleportation machine so captain kirk or
whoever it is they go and stand in this
machine and then the machine
seems to transfer the
them physically from one place to
another
so their body in in the machine
disappears and the body reappears
somewhere else but it's the truth is
that it's a copy of their body that
appears there it's a copy of their
consciousness the original body and the
original consciousness is destroyed
so you know that's the conundrum
if you create a copy of your
consciousness in some machine even if it
were possible it's not you who is there
it's a copy
so you are going to eventually die
anyway even if a copy of you survives
somewhere
so you know that that's the
that's the conundrum of of
these hypothetical scenarios that even
if you can create a copy of your
consciousness
you
your consciousness is going to
eventually
meet a demise
all right let's take some more questions
there are lots of questions
yes lotra asks what could be the reasons
that people who came out of africa chose
to stay in the indian subcontinent and
not somewhere else in the arabian land
which is closer to africa
well the conditions
in the indian subcontinent were best
suited for having a long-term permanent
residence
so when this out of africa migration
happened it is believed that the arabian
region was at the time kind of green it
was not a desert at the time
so the climate was such that you could
live there you could sustain life there
there were trees there was vegetation
there were animals you could hunt and
all but that was a transient phase
eventually it all dried out and
became desert
so the people who came out of africa
that small band of humans who came out
of africa they kept traveling they kept
moving and they kept looking for some
place where you can have
a permanent long-term habitation
and that place which they eventually
found was the indian subcontinent
the indian subcontinent was best suited
for living
on a permanent basis it was enormous
it was fertile there was lots of
vegetation there were forests
there's plenty of wildlife and animals
if you want to hunt and so on and the
climate was neither too hot nor too cold
and so on you know
and there was plenty of rainfall
so it was the best place they could have
possibly hoped for and that is the
reason why they chose to stay in the
indian subcontinent
not somewhere
in arabia or any any other place but
eventually
humans are a migratory species
even after settling down in india
in the indian subcontinent eventually
you had migrations happening all over
the place
so
eventually humans went eastwards they
went northwards out of india they went
westwards out of india populated europe
and so on and we came into contact with
other hominin hominid species such as
the neanderthals
the denisovans even possibly homo
habilis and so on
because there are a number of ancient
lineages that we find in our dna that
there are non-homo sapiens so we know
that we
all non-african humans have a certain
percentage about two to four percent of
neanderthal dna it's like having one
great great great grandparent or one
great grandparent who was a neanderthal
and we also have
depending on where you look
people have denisovan heritage one or
two percent of that
and certain
shadow populations that could be perhaps
homo habilis or something else
so eventually people did migrate all
over the place out of india as well but
india was the first founders zone
of the out of africa migration because
it was the best place and the most
suitable place for having
a very long term
human habitation
right let's see some more questions
krishna asks could you please talk about
dna test services such as myheritage and
23andme
and why some of the indians so many
youtube videos have european connections
uh so these are these are testing
services in which i think you
provide them a sample of your dna it's
usually a saliva a sample of a saliva
you they they are they send you a
package in which there is a
sample collection thing in which you
swab the interior of your mouth
and you place that in the receptable or
something
and you mail it to them and they will
test that for your dna they will
sequence your dna and tell you what are
your uh what kind of heritage you have
so that's what these dna test services
do it's i don't know what it costs maybe
100 200 or something like that
uh
so the question is why do some indians
so many youtubers so many youtube videos
why do indians have a european
connection well because there is a
connection like i said india is the
original founder zone
it is from india that migrations
happened all over eurasia into the east
of asia to the west of asia into europe
and so on and so forth even in the past
five thousand years maybe you had
multiple waves of migrations of indians
out of india into europe the yamnaya
uh those people who
conquered europe about five thousand or
four and a half thousand years ago and
almost replaced
the european male genetics those were
indians
those were of indian origin they they
were of their haplogroup was r1b which
is a descendant of the indian origin r1
haplogroup
so there is a very deep connection
between india and europe
um
so so that's the reason why so many
indians will have european connection
but
it is portrayed in such a manner that
the connection has come from europe into
india that's what is always
that's the way it is always portrayed
that is the
that is the the mainstream perspective
that they are trying to perpetuate that
whatever connection between is is there
between india and europe genetic
connection has come from europe into
india and not the other way around
that's what they are trying to
perpetuate and that is a complete
fabrication there is so much evidence
now
that totally debunks this claim of this
aryan invasion or migration from europe
into india it's the other way round but
to
to answer in short that is the reason
why so many indians will have be will
will be found to have some sort of
european connection
and when these uh
dna testing services give you the the
report
they're going to portrait in such a way
that your ancestors lived in europe and
then they came into india
so that's the that's the mainstream
perspective that has been
uh prevalent since the 19th century
since the colonial days the aryan
invasion perspective and that's still
prevalent in europe and in indian
academia and in the popular imagination
of most indians because that's what they
have been taught but that is
not correct
ishwara moody says
which is better single party or
multi-party system in democracy my
question
why do we even need political parties
why can't you just have
candidates who stand for election
unaffiliated to any party why do we need
parties parties are
like it's it's a herd of sheep with a
certain agenda why do
people need to follow a certain agenda
why can't you just stand for election
and your only agenda should be to serve
the constituency that has elected you
why do we even need a party system
think beyond the box
the party system
it serves certain purposes it it uh
it kind of perpetuates certain
ways of doing politics which is not
really necessary it is something that
has come out of europe again it's
something something that has come out
from the uk from from england and that
has been transposed into
onto india
right so ask yourselves do we need
political parties i i do agree that you
know in this day and age in the current
political climate when you have so much
going on
you need people who are like-minded to
get together and that can be termed as a
political party
and so on so
so what is better which system is better
you know what it doesn't matter which
system is there as long as it serves the
country
whether you have a single party system
you have a two-party system you have a
75-party system you have a dictatorship
you have a monarchy you have an imperial
system you have a system that is
decentralized it doesn't matter what
system is it is
the main part
as long as it ensures the long-term
success and prosperity of the people and
the country that system is good
i don't care whether it is a
single-party system a ten-party system
multi-party system dictatorship
democracy monarchy doesn't matter
as long as it ensures the long-term
prosperity success of the people and the
country it is fine by me
that's the answer
someday says should the quad give nukes
to taiwan no
nobody ever offers nukes to anyone that
sort of technology well actually it's
happened once
once it happened when
the american president kennedy
offered india nuclear weapons technology
he offered mr nehru
the great great shri
jawaharlal nehru the great panditji
president kennedy offered nehru
he offered to transfer american nuclear
weapons technology to india and he
offered nehru
the chance to make india asia's first
nuclear power
he offered to help india detonate asia's
first nuclear weapon and mr nehru
refused this
and therefore china was able to become
the first nuclear weapons power in in
asia the thing is apart from this one
instance one nobody has ever offered
nuclear weapons technology to others
except as proxies and so on i mean even
the chinese
transferred low-level nuclear weapons
technology to pakistan to offset india
to counter balance india and so on
but i do not think that the quad should
do that i don't think the quad will do
that
and even if taiwan were
were to come in possession of nuclear
weapons
would it really work for them
because
one of the reasons why taiwan is so
compromised is because all of their uh
many of their businesses
are deeply infiltrated by the chinese
and so on so it's a complicated
situation i do not think the quad will
offer news to taiwan the quad is india
australia
the us and japan
so only two of these
four countries are nuclear weapons
powers
india and the us
now
is india willing to antagonize china
by transferring nuclear weapons to
taiwan that would be an extraordinarily
grave provocation
and would the u.s be willing to
uh
offer nuclear weapons to taiwan they
don't need to they have nuclear
submarines patrolling that region all
the time
so there are nuclear weapons there in
the region
and they also have
ballistic missiles etc that can deliver
nuclear weapons so the us
has positioned itself as the guarantor
of security for taiwan
and as such they have the nuclear heft
the nuclear might
to offset the chinese and to keep them
keep the chinese in check and therefore
there is no real reason
to
actually transfer nuclear weapons to
taiwan so that's the reason why it will
not happen
illuminati creek says can india launch
an invasion of tibet
i think it's a little early to consider
that possibility india needs to develop
its military
might much more than what it is right
now
we need a much more powerful air force
to provide this the necessary air power
and we need
uh
significantly more tanks if if we want
to
launch an invasion of tibet
of course tanks cannot cross the
himalayas but one can find ways of
air dropping tanks via helicopters etc
if we have sufficient numbers of
helicopters and so on so you know it's a
complicated thing i don't think india is
currently in a position to be able to
contemplate such a thing seriously
but in the future if we develop our
military might more
if we
kind of double our air force strength
and so on then we may be able to do that
in the future but it's going to take at
least 10 years minimum
to be able to reach that sort of uh
level of capability
of military capability
amok chawan says what is the importance
of the citizen in geopolitics and what
can we the citizens of india do
for india in geopolitics
unfortunately there's not much the
citizens can do the best you can do is
elect the right leaders
the right kind of leader who
knows how to deal
with various geopolitical scenarios
so that is the best we can do apart from
that there is
no real role of the citizen of the
individual
in geopolitics which is a game that is
played at the global level
uh that is great power competition
it is where you move these big pieces on
the chessboard
aircraft carriers
destroyers submarines
armed forces air force
assets and so on and also your
diplomatic assets
you go you create alliances and networks
of power and all that so this is done at
the highest level
of governance
the citizens
unfortunately unfortunately cannot
participate in this and there are so
many state secrets citizens are not
aware of
right
and so on so there's not really much a
citizen
an individual can contribute to the
nation on the geopolitical scale
the best thing we can do
is to elect
the right leaders the strongest and best
possible leaders who can serve the
country in the right way
on the geopolitical domain
ashish ranjan says how did japan get so
powerful in having such a great human
resource
um
let me try and understand what that
means
so japan does have an excellent
industrial system
it has
the most advanced
industrial system in the world the best
technologies come out of japan it is the
most technologically advanced society on
the planet
it is technologically more advanced than
the united states than european
countries than china than anybody else
so how did this happen
it's because the japanese system was
reformed
beginning with the meiji reformation
i think in the sometime in the second
half of the 19th century
so that was a conscious effort to
industrialize and westernize japan
it succeeded in the industrialization
front but it failed in eradicating
buddhism etc from japan
so that was the first thing and then
after the uh
debacle of the second world war in which
japan was
was defeated very badly it was nuked
twice etc
the japanese came under american
occupation which
well you could say it still continues
today but the japanese rebuilt their
economy
and they turned it into a very efficient
machine
industrial machine they
they emphasized on
performance on meritocracy and all that
and this is a system that
enabled them to rebuild the country out
of the ashes of the second world war to
create a very powerful economy
which was
the number two economy in the world
until the 1980s or 1990s i think
and then it fell into a recession and so
on but it is still an extraordinarily
strong economy and it is one of the
most
advanced industrial sectors in the world
so it's
it's uh it's a long process it did not
happen in in five or ten years
it is something that began in the second
half of the 19th century and its legacy
was carried forward year after year
decade after decade and that is the
reason why japan was able to
become so powerful
in
its industrial
technological and other sectors even the
military for itself even even today
japan is a very powerful military it is
a very powerful navy the chinese are
afraid of the japanese submarine force
and so on japan is also
considered to be a shadow nuclear power
which means that they can
if they need they can come up with
nuclear weapons next week
so and they also have delivery systems
excellent rockets and so on
so that is the reason why they have been
able to achieve this level of competence
and excellence
in all these spheres
okay some more questions
bluebird03 asks can china divide india
into many small countries well they wish
they they want to do that they have many
of their thinkers strategists even
generals
have written about this in the past in
the past two decades and even before
that
and they have been trying to ferment
insurgencies etc in india in various
parts of the country
for decades
so it is very much
a desire of theirs to break up to
balkanize india it is one of their great
dreams
and it is one of the great dreams of
pakistan as well to do this so they
that's why these two countries analyze
they wish to do it can they do it well
it all depends on us
on what
uh
policies and strategies we adopt
i mean
we everybody has enemies it all depends
on you how strong you become through
your own efforts
and then it's up to you whether you
allow such uh
such nefarious schemes to succeed or not
so china does wish to do it but i don't
think it is possible for china to do it
right now
india does have internal problems lots
of internal problems and so on
but india is still
as of today
strong enough to withstand such
attempts
to divide it from within but we have to
be ever vigilant we have to
find ways of quickly resolving all the
internal
problems etc that we have
in order to ensure that this never
happens
so i would say as of today china is not
in
uh
in a in a position to be able to
divide india or to break india up but it
does desire to do that
asks is china's next target arunachal
pradesh after taiwan
i don't think china would want to do a
genuine
military misadventure vis-a-vis india in
arunachal pradesh or anywhere else
because
well india
is not an aggressive and expansionist
country but i think india's military is
strong enough to defend its territory
and if china crosses certain red lines
then china can well
can face serious trouble
so
china's main goal main objective is
taiwan china's economy is crumbling
right now it is completely stalled there
is almost no economic growth
there are several crisis the ever grand
crisis and so on there are many other
problems that are that have been hidden
and have not have been kind of sweat
swept under the carpet so china seems to
be
undergoing some kind of economic crisis
right now
which may
uh influence its leaders to perhaps make
some rash choices
and do things that would not be
advisable for their own
interests so it is possible that china
may try and invade taiwan sometime
in the near
or medium term future
china is uh behaving very aggressively
with child with taiwan right now all
these aerial incursions
by the chinese air force into taiwanese
airspace and so on
so the question is what is china
actually planning to do is it planning
to invade taiwan sometime soon
and if it invades taiwan what should
india respond
how should india respond what should our
response be like so these are scenarios
that are evolving right now i do not
really think
the chinese would be stupid enough to
target arunachal pradesh
they could
i think they will not succeed
india has very strong defenses india has
very strong plans of defending its
territory if the chinese were to try it
they would
suffer a very
bad defeat i am certain of that
and that would undermine the
chinese communist party's legitimacy in
the eyes of its citizens that that could
undermine
the very basis
of
power of the chinese communist party i
don't think therefore that china would
target arunachal pradesh
if it would it would face a terrible
defeat and if it would cross a certain
red line then india does have the
capability
to stay to send china back into the
stone age so
they know that they
should
they are well advised
not
to
try any misadventure
when it comes to india's territorial
boundaries
okay
next question let's see
jerry asks why is the indian government
not showing any kind of interest in
archaeological excavations
well
i would
i cannot answer on behalf of the indian
government
i have said this many times in the past
it's very disappointing i think india's
ministry of tourism and culture
is
one of the
least performing ministries one of the
poorest
performing ministries in
the government
they're
they're basically doing nothing
essentially
i am not sure if the asi et cetera comes
under them most likely it does and the
asi is another
very badly performing organization
institution whatever you want to call it
why is there no interest in archaeology
why is there no interest in
in in uncovering our real history etc
why is nothing being done i
don't know i wish i had answers i do not
have answers i am very disappointed
it's been seven years and yet nothing
has been done
so it's very disappointing that's all i
can see i don't know why it is the way
it is it's disappointing
deepan bhattacharya says can dark matter
be discovered through using
gravitational lensing we can detect the
presence of dark matter through
gravitational lensing so gravitational
lensing is when the presence of a mass
distorts the the path of light
which causes galaxies and other objects
to to appear distorted when we look at
them
so when you have
nothing apparently between you and the
galaxy and yet the galaxy is distorted
it is curved or whatever in the form of
an einstein ring or whatever in that
case you know that there is
the presence of an invisible mass there
which is dark matter so we can detect
the presence
of dark matter using gravitational
lensing but we cannot detect what the
dark matter is
using gravitational lensing so these are
two separate things we can find the
location
of
dark matter distributions using these
phenomena but we can't tell what
dark matter is what kind of particle it
is
through gravitational lensing
donggar singh johann says is capitalism
and privatization necessary for the
development of india
or is there any other way
i think the fastest way to develop the
country
in the current scenario is through
capitalism and privatization
that is the fastest way to do it
uh there are better ways of course i
mean if you look at the
if you study the arthashastra there is a
whole
section on economics which is
non-capitalistic
right
so
that is a better way but it would take a
much longer amount of time to build up
india to that status which it typica it
historically had
of being the world's largest economy
so to achieve that status very quickly
as quickly as is humanly possible we
would need to
adopt capitalism and privatization that
is
that is something we can adopt as a
temporary short to medium term solution
and later on as india becomes more
prosperous we can change the system
to suit our civilization and culture
better capitalism is all about seeking
endless
profits
endless expansion
quarter upon quarter profits quarter
upon quarter
expansion of companies
you cannot have
run away
infinite expansion
on a finite planet
it is eventually going to destroy all
the resources and destroy the entire
planet and that is what we are doing
right now
this process this capitalism
has been uh
in play
for at least a couple of centuries
exploitation of the planet seeing
everything in the planet as resources to
be used
and today all of what we are seeing all
the climate change all the pollution all
the deforestation all the
uh pollution of the ocean with plastics
etc it's all a consequence of this
this mentality of using the planet as
nothing more than a resource to be
exploited
so
that is a consequence of of
uncontrolled capitalism so this is a
problem
capitalism if it is allowed to go on
will destroy the planet and i am when i
criticize capitalism you should not take
it to mean that i am in favor
of uh what's the opposite communism
socialism is it no marxism no i am not
in favor of communism marxism socialism
either
there are better ways the indian way is
the best way what we have followed for
thousands of years we had the world's
greatest
and most massive economy without
indulging in such practices that would
destroy the planet
but
right now if you want to compete with
the other economies we have to go the
same way
so temporarily we need to privatize and
we need to
use the tactics and strategies of
capitalism for now
truth digger says if china invades
taiwan what are the priorities for india
if or when china invades taiwan
india needs to immediately without
wasting even one hour
india needs to immediately
secure
nepal bhutan and sri lanka
that's what india needs to do
immediately the moment the chinese
invade taiwan
secure nepal secure bhutan
secure
sri lanka
now i am not advocating an outright
invasion and occupation of these
countries
maybe some of these places will need
indian booths
on their soil
in the case of sri lanka it may not be
required but india's navy will need to
become involved and safeguard
sri lanka
in the case of nepal and bhutan we may
have no option but to send indian armed
forces to secure these territories from
possible chinese
uh
misadventures
so that's what india needs to do the
moment the chinese invade that one we
need to secure nepal bhutan and sri
lanka that's what india needs to do
in my opinion
okay harsh kumar asks in the future if
the us would be able to counter china
then their next target would be india
what can india do to prevent that
the best policy
for india
is to become as strong as possible
as quickly as possible
if you are economically and militarily
strong enough
then nobody
can harm you
so india needs to right now india needs
india right now as of today is not a
great power we are not a great power
today we are maybe a middle power at
best
today
so as of today we need to play the game
of geopolitics we need to have alliances
or quasi alliances
with countries such as the us which are
far away
in order to offset china which is an
aggressive and expansionist
nation there is no such thing as china's
peaceful rise
so as of today
it is in our favor it is in our interest
to ally with countries like the us
australia japan and any other country
which shares our our world view
but in the long run if the us prevails
then certainly they will not want india
to rise too much
the us doesn't want
any kind of competition
and neither does china
so the only option for india the only
long-term
option for india is to rise again
economically and militarily
we need to ensure that we are so strong
that nobody dares
to contemplate
you know uh targeting
us in any way either through economic
means or through military means so that
has to be india's long-term objective
and that is something india needs to
achieve in the next 10 20 years
maximum
to at least make sure that we are safe
from any
any uh
malign force that would seek to
destroy us
red chile asks will india capture china
i do not want india to capture china
what what will india gain by capturing
china
we have never been an expansionist
country it is not part of our cultural
civilization and i would not advocate
trying to capture china
uh what we need to do is to free tibet
so that we have a peaceful northern
border
we need to free tibet and we need to
decontaminate tibet from all the chinese
influences that is all we need to do
there is no point trying to capture
china china is so far away tibet is of
course our neighbor but tibet is not
truly chinese territory it is
temporarily in the hands of china
once we free tibet that has to be the
end of it what is the point of going all
the way far away to china thousands of
kilometers away
and capturing it what do we gain from
that
we will be
over stretching ourselves if we try that
so
so my answer is no india will not
capture china india should not have any
such uh
aspirations what india should aspire for
is to have a powerful economy again a
strong military again and to have a
peaceful and stable
northern border which is the tibetan
border we need to free tibet or
insurance freedom
and we need a peaceful and stable
western border
which means that we need to deal with
the pakistan issue
and we need to regain our land access to
afghanistan
so these are the things that india needs
to achieve
in the short to medium term future
and that's what india needs to do not
think of capturing china it serves no
purpose for india
tony stark says why is the history of
china and japan not included in school
textbooks
my name is arkab energy well arka
even the true history of india is not
included in these in india's school
textbooks right
i mean we are taught very small
uh portions of indian history and that
to sanitize and distorted portions of
india's history we are not taught about
any of the great native dynasties
emperors kings queens
and
most of our history we don't even know
about it it's not taught
so if we don't even learn our own
history do you really expect the
textbooks to teach
chinese history or japanese history or
european issue or anything
no
it simply won't happen
it is of course beneficial to teach
world history as well as apart from
indian history
but that is something that will happen
only when the indian education system is
reformed
in such a way that it actually serves
the purpose of educating
the people of india
so the reason why it's this all of this
is not happening is because our
education system is still
deeply colonized it is still following
the same patterns that you had
in
the education system the british imposed
upon india in the 19th century it is
very much a continuation of the same
system
and that's why we are not taught
either our own history properly or the
history of any other
of any other culture or country
write some more questions
aryan kumar asks where the khiljis and
ludi's weather turks are afghans i hope
my question gets picked well your
question got picked
uh the khiljis where mom looks i think
no i don't think i know the khiljis were
mom looks so people like allah abdeen
khilji etc
these were mom look so what is what are
the mom looks
the mom looks where slaves
this was a slave dynasty
the word mamluk means slave in arabic
now
a slave can be from any part of the
world you had egyptian mamluks
you had turkic mom looks and you had
iran and mamluks also i expect
but the kaljis the khiljis were turkic
mom looks
so you had these
so the arabs would
take
these uh
people as slaves
and then they would employ them in the
armed forces as soldiers and if they
showed sufficient
tactical and strategic abilities then
they would be elevated to the position
of a general if they showed even more
abilities they would be
given the
role or task of administering a certain
province but they would still be
considered to be slaves they would still
be officially slaves
and eventually as certain dynasties
crumbled these slave administrators
became kings or rulers in their own
right
and that is what the
mamluk dynasty was
these were former slaves who
conquered parts certain parts of india
on behalf of their masters but
eventually they became independent of
their masters and they became rulers of
whatever portion of india they had
conquered so aladdin khilji and his
dynasty was a mamluk dynasty a slave
dynasty they were
turks i believe the lodis were also
turks
if i i'm not 100 sure about that but i
i am positive that the lodis too were
where
mom where were turks
so that's the answer but i would request
you to please verify that
this is a good question by garema how is
social media influencing the next
generation of india
so it is very influential in india
social media
today you have a twitter instagram
youtube
whatsapp and um what else you had tick
tock which has been banned now and so on
so you have all these different social
media platforms
that are very influential
especially
among the children among the teenagers
and young adults very influential so uh
twitter and facebook facebook too right
so twitter and facebook became prominent
i think about 10 or so years ago in
india
it kind of revolutionized
the entire
cultural and social landscape in india
because
it was a very big boon initially
because for the first time in a thousand
years
the people of india were able to express
themselves and connect with each other
this happened for the first time in
in in a thousand years
the people of india were able to express
themselves and
voice their opinions
criticize
the government criticize the media
criticize the powers that be and so on
and they were able to connect with each
other so that's how people from all
across india were able to
connect with each other create
have friendships and
various kinds of relationships either
professional relationships business
relationships or whatever right
so social media was a great boon
at that time
then slowly you had all the
all these policies that were that began
to be implemented
which kind of uh stifled social media
there were now we have a great deal a
great amount of social media censorship
especially on twitter right in which
you're not able to you're not allowed to
express your opinions freely and so on
and so forth
and because of that you find that
certain
political ideologies are allowed to
express themselves whereas certain other
ideologies are not allowed to express
themselves
so you find that
a platform like twitter for instance has
become extremely left-leaning
in india it is very much pro opposition
anti-government
and when you talk about the opposition
you understand what sort of political
and religious leanings that signifies
so you find that
people are not able to express certain
opinions on twitter
and because of that
it influences these uh
inexperienced youngsters
in uh
imbibing and absorbing
certain
political leanings and ideologies and
you see that very very very strongly in
the opinions that youngsters express you
know so
this is actually a form of social
engineering
uh
so that's what's happening right now so
social
so social media was initially a great
boon for india
but today it is becoming dangerous for
india because it is essentially foreign
interference
in the internal matters of india you see
uh
certain politicians getting banned
i think uh
certain mps were forced to delete
certain tweets because tweeter did not
like them
i'm just talking about twitter here but
many of it applies much of it applies to
certain other social media platforms as
well i'm sure
so you have
the absence of freedom of speech you
have censorship
and because of that certain political
leanings and ideologies are promoted
and that is influencing
the youngsters in india
and you can see the effect of that in
the
opinions they express and so on
so it is dangerous
it is interference by foreign powers
in india's internal matters
and something needs to be done about it
right so so that's what's happening
okay this is a question by sumit
was india
and africa part of the same land mass
thousands of years ago
if so
does the migration from africa involve
migration from india as well okay we
have to understand the chronology india
and africa yes sumit were very much part
of the same land mass
about a hundred million years ago
and then india separated from africa
because of tectonic activity
and it began
a long journey of thousands of
kilometers
from africa
all the way into the eurasian land mass
so this journey took
at least 60 70 million years
and eventually india collided with the
eurasian landmass and this enormous
cataclysmic collision which happened in
very slow motion
it led to the emergence of the himalayan
mountain range which is this tallest
mountain ridge
on the planet
so this happened over
a very long period of time tens of
millions of years
right
now
if you look at the history of humanity
homo sapiens is less than 250 000 years
old up let's say it's a quarter of a
million years old
and the earliest oldest humans
are about 2 million years old so humans
and chimpanzees diverged about 2 million
years ago
by the time india was already part of
the eurasian land mass
so when india and africa were together
about 100 million years approximately
ago there was no humans
we did not have humans at the time
we had dinosaurs that ruled our planet
so this
this movement of india from africa into
into eurasia took millions of years
and this greatly predates the emergence
of humans as a species
so the migration from africa
it has nothing to do to do with the
tectonic activity which occurs over
geological time scales humanity is is is
very recent extremely recent
homo sapiens is about a quarter of a
million years old
approximately
so so to to
summarize my answer
the
geological
activity the tectonic activity has
nothing to do with the out of africa
migration of humans because there was no
humanity at the time
there were no human beings on the planet
at the time
okay some more questions some more
questions
krish asks uh any practical tips for
studying the history of a particular
place or era
i sometimes get lost while studying
foreign familiarity
reliability
relatability gone
okay what advice can i give for studying
the history of a particular praise place
of era the best advice i can give you is
to not rely on a single book or a single
video
try and look at this
specific place or era
from multiple perspectives from the
perspectives of multiple researchers
multiple authors
so read multiple books
read as many articles as you can
research papers journal articles
national geographic articles or whatever
you like
and only then will you be able to get a
comprehensive picture
of
the true
uh
nature of that place or that particular
era because if you rely on one person
on one author or one youtuber or
whatever it is then you will get only
one perspective
that's why you should look at different
angles and try and
see as many different
perspectives
of different authors and researchers as
possible that's the right way to study
history
so that's
the answer it takes time but that's the
best way to
learn and grow
where does india stand in the next
decade as a civilization
and should we become a hard power or
remain a soft power
uh what major changes should be brought
in the education system thank you i
think i have it i have an entire episode
on the education system so you can look
at that right
i think it's episode 30 31 thereabouts
uh the first question is where does
india stand in the next decade as a
civilization india is no longer a
civilization india is now merely a
nation state
india is not a civilization because
india's
because india's institutions india's law
and india's india's laws and india's
constitution are not rooted in indian
culture
and therefore india is no longer a
civilization india no longer has that
status
india ceased to be a civilization on
august 15 1947. india is now merely
a nation state which is
tragic
should we become a hard power or remain
a soft power
india should become a hard power soft
power is a mirage
i
i don't understand why
so many indians are so obsessed with
soft power soft powers of powers of
power soft power is useless it's
worthless unless it is backed up by
actual hard power the only real power is
hard power so that's what india needs to
pursue
right i think i have some questions
which i had selected some people had
asked me let me take up some of those
questions i have three questions from
the comments that i picked up
so here is question number one this is
by andrew
andrew asks can you talk about the diet
during the vedic times
has vegetarianism always been prominent
in india
so when we talk about the vedic times
the vedic era is the
earliest literary era in india that's
where the oldest literature
of our civilization comes from the rig
veda and the other vedas the puranas may
actually be even older than that but if
you look at the oldest corpus of
literature of our civilization and
culture
then we find that
vegetarian vegetarianism is the is
regarded as the
superior
lifestyle choice
so india's culture has always
regarded non-violence as the highest
idea
and non-violence of course includes
not slaughtering helpless animals
so uh vegetarianism has always been
regarded as the highest ideal that's the
superior way of living
of course it was not a compulsion it was
not forced on people
india has always had some people certain
population certain parts of the
population that
were non-vegetarian who would eat meat
it's always been there
but
non-veg but vegetarianism was always
regarded as the highest ideal so
the diet was mixed i would say during
veg vedic times maybe the majority of
the population
was vegetarian but there would always be
some people who are not vegetarian and
the archaeological record of india shows
this we find plenty of evidence of fish
hooks and harpoons from various eras of
india civilization including the
harappan era the harappan phase of
india's civilization and so on and so
forth so we know that
people have eaten meat throughout
india's history
and yet we also know that
our
that india's
ancient texts in india's culture have
always promoted
vegetarianism as the superior way of
living so i would say that india's diet
during vedic times would
possibly have been predominantly
vegetarian but some people would
certainly be eating meat for sure
the next question is uh
okay this asks that
i'm not sure how to pronounce the name
but the question is that i was wondering
what do you think about gobekli tepe
you have claimed that the indus
civilization is the oldest civilization
but research on gobekli they proves
otherwise okay good question i'm glad
you asked this
so uh as we know
the oldest archaeological sites in india
are about nine and a half or ten
thousand
years old
and this is the earliest pre-harappan
phase they call it
of india's civilization now gobekli tepe
which is a locate which is a settlement
in
anatolia eastern turkey present-day
eastern turkey go back
is about 11 000 years old so it predates
uh the earliest known archaeological
site in the indus
region
so does it mean that
this
is
an older civilization so to answer this
question we have to ask ourselves
what is a civilization
if we find one settlement somewhere
does that represent a civilization
if you look at the size of gobekli
one would say that it represents a
community of maybe 200 or 500 people or
a thousand people
is a community of 000 people a
civilization
does it represent a civilization even if
you have one single settlement one
single archaeological site
does that represent a
civilization or if you have a cluster of
five archaeological sites
does that make a civilization
no
a civilization is an enormous thing
if you look at the indus valley or
harappan phase of india's civilization
it
spanned a geographical region that was
larger than egypt and mesopotamia put
together
it was an enormous geographical region
there are thousands
of archaeological sites in this region
that is a civilization all these
archaeological sites
show
characteristics of the same culture of
the same people the same standardization
of weights and measures the same script
the same kind of pottery and so on
across
thousands of years
that is a civilization
one archaeological site is not a
civilization even a cluster of five
archaeological sites is not a
civilization a civilization is much
bigger than that much bigger
and this is not the fault of the viewers
many of you have the question it's not
your fault that you don't understand
this
if you look at india's textbooks history
textbooks they don't teach you what a
civilization is
if you look at india's media every time
they find some new archaeological site
killer d
shiva galai
or somewhere else they will say oh we
have a new killer d civilization we have
a new civic li civilization every single
archaeological site is represented or
portrayed as a new civilization
this is idiotic
it is the fault of the indian media of
the indian academic and education system
that people don't understand what a
civilization is a civilization is an
enormous thing you need tens of
thousands hundreds of thousands of
people to make a civilization it needs
to have a common culture a common
unifying language
it needs to have
institutions
and laws
that are rooted in the native indigenous
culture and so on that's what makes a
civilization a single archaeological
site is not a civilization so now
government
is just one site there are two three
other sites around it that is not
a civilization it's just a cluster of
archaeological sites
it is certainly older than the oldest
known indus valley
archaeological site but we should also
understand that we have excavated less
than one percent
of the archaeological sites in the
sindhu region
there are thousands
of unexplored archaeological sites
along the river systems along the river
saraswati along the other rivers
that have never been excavated
once we start doing that we will find
older and older archaeological sites i
think india's archaeological record will
go back
at least another ten thousand years
way older than go back
and anything else
so that's where we are today so that's
what i have to say about go back
i
still uh
stand by what i have said that in the
indus valley the in the harappan phase
of india's civilization is the oldest
phase of any civilization anywhere in
the world
right i hope that explains it
one more question this is by sayad
mthiaz anwar who is from pakistan
so
uh
india says pharaoh ramses sarkar 1450
bce went north of egypt to protect the
egyptian realm at the time
from invaders called the mithani empire
he was outflanked by them initially
because they had new technology the
chariot that the egyptians had never
seen before they captured some of these
chariots engineered their own
that were even better than the bizani
and then they used it to defy defeat the
hittites etc the question is i have seen
pictures of lord krishna on chariots
that i believe predates the bhitani so
is it possible that the methane learned
the technology from the folks living in
the subcontinent
or the mittani themselves were offshoots
of the people living in the
subcontinents what do you think
good question sir
so
who are these mithani you are right the
egyptians pharaoh ramses i think it was
uh went northwards to
to engage in warfare with these people
the mithani the hittites etc
and
so the question is
who were the mitani
so archaeological
evidence shows
that the methane
had a ruling class an aristocracy that
spoke
vedic
sanskrit late vedic sanskrit
so this is known from
a number of
sources a number of archaeological
evidences there is a
a horse training manual by a kikuli
horsemaster by a mittani horse master
named kikuli in which he writes
he has written the horse training manual
in the horyan language the local
language
but he has used certain technical terms
in sanskrit because there are no
technical terms
for those those terms are not
translatable into the local language so
he was forced to use sanskrit
terminology in there and then there is a
treaty an official treaty between the
methane empire
and the hittites i think
in which
the vedic gods
mitra varuna etc
etc were invoked as witnesses
so you have multiple pieces of evidence
that show that the methane
had an indo-aryan so-called indo-aryan
sanskrit-speaking aristocracy ruling
class and we know the names of the kings
tashiratha and so on all sanskrit names
so
what this tells us is that the mithani
are
the evidence
of a population that migrated westwards
out of india about 2000 bce or around
1500 bce
and they
conquered or settled in this region
anatolia
and they became the ruling class the
aristocracy right that's what we know
and their their capital was called
vashukhani vashukhanda is a sanskrit
word which means a mind of treasure
so that's what we know about the methane
now we also had the hittites were again
an indo-european sanskrit-speaking
people most likely
and then you had an invasion of egypt
by a people from the north
approximately
1450 bce somewhere around that uh time
period
these people came from the north they
invaded and conquered egypt and ruled it
for 100 or 150 years
the egyptians called them the hick sauce
the hexos invaders
these invaders worshipped a thunder god
that sounds like indra they had
technology like the chariot they had
bronze weapons advanced weapons and so
on which were all introduced into egypt
because of their invasion and conquest
so
uh if you look at
the mainstream consensus of history of
historians in the west they claim that
these were middle eastern people
uh
who worshipped some babylonian god or
something that they tried to say that
this was the god
baal not the god indra and so on
but i think that
once we dig deeper into this matter we
will find that even these invaders the
hicks wear of indo-aryan origin most
likely
so to answer your question mthiaz
it is clear that the mithani are
a population
of ancient indians
who migrated westwards and settled down
in
present-day
anatolia in present-day turkey
and uh
yeah they had the chariot they had
advanced technology that the egyptians
did not have at the time and it's
because of these mithani the hittites
and the invading hicks who were very
closely related to these guys
that's how all this technology made its
way into egypt
now about lord krishna on chariots and
all yeah we know lord krishna was the
charioteer
of of the great warrior arjuna and so on
so yes it is quite possible that this
technology made its way westwards from
india
with the mithani
and then eventually it spread into egypt
from there so very interesting question
very good question
and i'm glad you are showing interest in
this in your own heritage great to see
that
okay let's take some more questions
reika asks
sokratis came to india and met in indian
yogi
and discussed human life please answer i
i don't know there is no evidence as far
as as far as i understand
that socrates ever came to india so
it's possible that me he may have had
some interactions with
indian philosophers in greece because
indians used to travel everywhere
so it is entirely possible this may have
happened but i don't think there is any
record or any evidence
of socrates ever having actually come
physically to india
so to the best of my knowledge this has
not happened this did not happen
kishore asks why is punjabi so similar
to the hindi language well not only
punjabi all these languages are quite
similar
these are all
languages that
our daughter or granddaughter
or great great great granddaughter
languages of our ancestral
civilizational language sanskrit
and that's why they're all so similar
they're also closely interrelated
whether it is punjabi or hindi or
marwari or gujarati or sindhi or
bhojpuri
[Music]
and so on and so forth even southern
indian languages like
like kannada telugu
tamil
malayalam
etc have a great deal great amount of
sanskrit vocabulary
and so on
so it is all because our
ancient ancestral civilizational
language was sanskrit
which is most likely the oldest known
language maybe tamil maybe some other
languages may be also quite old but i
think sanskrit is the oldest known
language
in human history
and that's why all of these languages
have so many commonalities so many
common features very similar grammar
very similar vocabulary and so on and so
forth that is the reason why
okay
some
more questions there are so many
interesting questions here
shyam asks is soft power a myth in
geopolitics yes soft power is of no use
in geopolitics soft power is useful when
you already have hard power and when you
can enforce
your writ in your culture across the
world
so soft power is something you should
pursue only after you become a proper
hard power
you can also certainly develop your soft
power your culture etc while
simultaneously developing hard power but
the emphasis always has to be on hard
power you cannot stop an invasion
with soft power
right
so that's why
it is a myth in geopolitics
as menor asks can a private institution
be established for teaching the real
history geopolitics and survive the
backlash in india well certainly a
private institution can be established
to do all this one could hire a number
of
talented historians and researchers
and one could commission a series of
books that teach the proper history of
india
that explained geopolitics etcetera that
would need funding
it it takes funding to create an
institution or an institute and to pay
the salaries of all these researchers
and
historians teachers etc
so yes it is certainly feasible
but it will take
a
sizable significant amount of resources
of money especially
so it is possible yes you're right
asks my views on celibacy i think
celibacy is a choice
that's all i can say about it
uh it has had a significant um
an important role to play in indian
history in in
culture in philosophy spiritualism all
that
but after all it is a person's
individual choice what path they want to
follow
it has its benefits and so on right so
it's all about what you want
individually
in your life
so based on that you can make a choice
of whether you want to remain celibate
or
or get married and live a worldly life
so it's a personal choice i would say
okay a couple more questions
ashrae asks where the yamnaya one of the
defeated tribes from the battle of the
ten kings
good question it is a possibility it all
depends on when this battle
took place
so we know that the yamnia rampaged
through europe about four and a half
thousand years ago
but we also know that about four and a
half thousand years ago was the mature
phase of the
so-called harappan era of india's
civilization when india was a large
enormous
urban
civilization
now the battle of the ten kings seems to
depict an india that was not urban
and india which was
much less populated than during the
harappan
era
so
if this battle took place maybe thousand
two thousand
years before
uh the harappan mature mature phase then
perhaps one of these
defeated clans
could have been the ancestors of the
yamna possibly so the possibility is
certainly there but we unfortunately
have not been able to comprehensively
and definitively
date
the battle of the ten kings even if we
can place it in a certain millennium
that would help significantly as of
today nobody has made the effort
which is disappointing but so i can't
really tell you for sure
whether the yamnaya were one of the
defeated clans or tribes but it is
certainly a possibility that needs to be
taken that needs to be considered
seriously
okay vedant asks we see towns in radar
and jammon kashmir are chinese language
names
can this be changed and will it create
geopolitical pressure on india from
china
okay so i have personally haven't
come across
towns in ladakh or jamun kashmir that
that have chinese names i personally
have never come across this so
so i'm not entirely sure if this is
correct
so but you know what i will i will
verify this i'll try and find if there
are any towns
in our territory that have chinese names
i think it's quite unlikely so
that's what i can say as of today as of
right now
right let's take
one more question perhaps
how can you
be so calm after knowing what's
happening in the world i am unable to
study after i started reading history
and watching the news please help
first of all i would
request you to i would i would suggest
it's not really beneficial to watch the
news cycle
it's it hypes everything up
it makes it feel like the world is
ending on a daily basis
there are all these so called debates
there are nothing more than shouting
matches you have 27 people on the screen
and they're all shouting at each other
it does i have stopped watching the news
for at least two years i have missed
nothing
that's the first thing i would say so i
think you could perhaps consider not
watching the news that much
studying history well you have to know
the facts about the world
the world is a complex place
things are not always the way they
should be
there is a lot of injustice there has
been especially in the case of india
uh
things we know what happened it's
terrible the past 1000 years have been
a terrible terrible phase of india's
history
but you know what there's no point
becoming uh
becoming unhappy
or not calm
things that are not in your control you
should not worry about them too much
what you can control is what you do with
your own personal life
i am ex i think you are a very young
person
so
what you can do to change the world or
shape the world to some extent
is develop yourself to the fullest
possible extent you can to your fullest
potential that is something you can
control so work on that
uh
place all your emphasis on that
poor invest all your energies and time
into developing yourself into the best
possible person you can be
and in once you do that you will be able
to have a positive impact
on
the shape of history possibly so that is
something that's in your control there
is no point getting upset or angry
or feeling helpless about things that
are not in your control right so that is
one way of looking at the world that
will ensure that you stay calm
and focused on the things that you
actually can control so that is what i
can say to you
ravi
okay let me take one more
change
one more question sorry one more
question
okay
if the rn invasion wasn't real then why
do people like the charts have more step
dna than others what is step dna
where did it come from
when they put a label like iranian
ancestry or step dna or or whatever
my question is what came before that
what is the ancestry of the so-called
step dna the step dna
is the yamnaya dnas
now what is the ancestry of the yamnayas
the yamnaya are all male they were male
conquerors
their petrolenial lineage was r1b
all right
that is their petrolenial lineage
r1b is a child lineage of the r1
patrilineal lineage now let me inform
you
that the r1 lineage and the r lineage
originated in
bharat wash
in the indian subcontinent and therefore
this step dna
itself came from india
and that is why there are people some
people in india who have this dna this
this lineage
and the geneticists are trying to
portray that as having come from the
central asian step
but that genetic cleanage of the central
asian step itself came from india before
that
they will not tell you this
and that is why
people
seem to have dna that came from central
asia but it is actually something that
came from out of india went to central
asia then came back into india
so that is the answer my friends
all right
that that is it for today
thank you so much for participating
thank you so much for your questions
i am very grateful that all you all
attend these sessions that you all ask
all of these wonderful questions
and we shall do this again tomorrow same
time same channel
so until then i will
say have a good day have a good night
take care and i'll see you tomorrow bye